{
  "reference_number": "9740",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": "This is the area of emissions which has shown the most growth and has the most potential to continue growing, and where we have\n real options to reduce this growth. We will have a much better chance of achieving our goals if we focus narrowly on something we\n can have a big impact on."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Emissions reduction targets should be set at a regional level to ensure that low emitting regions are not made to shoulder the\n burden for high emitting regions, and to ensure that regions with a low emissions profile are recognised as such. This would also\n encourage a more equal distribution of economic activity. There is also a huge need for recognition of the means of sequestering\n\n emissions to be more broadly recognised, as currently very little of the nations vegetative cover and stored carbon is recognised as\n providing a service. I would also like to add that it seems utterly pointless for a nation with as much natural and exotic forest cover,\n\n with such a small population to be paying another nation to 'sequester' carbon."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We could have a volcanic eruption and out targets would go out the window. Also our science is evolving which requires our\n legislation to evolve with it. (ie wetlands are great for biodiversity and water quality but are high emitters of methane which is still not\n recognised by agricultural emissions modelling on farm emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think you are better to have a ten and 15 budget, 5 years is not enough for business certainty."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As stated earlier, I believe the science will continue to change requiring flexibility in the way budgets are set and met."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "See above"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This makes sense"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The government should ensure the framework is set to ensure the prosperity and resilience of the New Zealand people. They should\nensure that the system 'transition' is not structured in a way that creates a burden on the economic system which is required to pay\n\nfor his transition. The government will need the support of its largest industry's and should therefore work in partnership with them"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This provision should simply be part of governance regardless of climate change, it is known as planning for the uncertain future."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Some areas will face different issues and this may be information which needs to be captured. However I would caution against\n\nsetting up so many administration levels that the mechanism becomes unwieldy and expensive to operate. I would put the onus of\nthis reporting on existing ministries."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I would like to highlight the fact that the discussion document was poorly written (leading) and unnecessarily inaccessible to non-\nacademic readers, which has resulted in a number of people ringing me to ask for an interpretation of said document. This clearly\n\nshows the document was not fit for purpose and failed to inform the people it was directed towards (the public). For this reason I\nbelieve the submissions recieved will be heavily biased toward academia and environmental lobby groups who have the means of\ndiseminating the information they would like to see recorded in submissions. I would also note that in its current form the document\n\ndoes little to clealy inform the reader of the implications of the different types of gasses being included (is methane increasing\nwarming or not?) or excluded in the bill, and the how these would be taxed and what the resulting social, economic and\n\nenvironemental landscape would look like; the inclusion of the pictorial model hardly does justice to what could be a hugely varied\nand largely unpresidented distortion of the economic environment as we know it. Lastly the reliance of planting trees is highly\n\nconcerning, given that globally planation forestry has increased on an immense scale and is therefore likely at some point to become\ndepressed (potentially disastrously so). There are also many assumed and unqualified assertions in the discussion document\nrelating to the improvement plantation forestry is 'known' to have on water quality, biodiversity and erosion. The government will be\n\naware that this is not true in some landscapes as evidenced by recent examples of erosion prone land suffering catastrophic damage\nfollowing harvest, and the flow-on effects in waterways, research in the space is ongoing. The public requires balanced information\n\nwhich is clear and unbias if they are to make an informed submission, something that the discussion document failed to provide."
    }
  ]
}
